Haoran Wan

Email: haoranwan97@gmail.com Website: wanhaoran.github.io Mobile: +86 18696020789

Research Interest

My current research interests are mobile and ubiquitous computing, including designing and implementing ubiquitous and wireless sensing systems for Internet-of-Things applications (localization, smart homes/buildings, vital sign monitoring/healthcare, and 3D human-mobile interaction). Besides, I have a broad interest in wireless network as well. Currently, most of my projects are based on acoustic signals on commercial-off-the-shelf mobile devices.

EDUCATION

Nanjing University Nanjing, China M.S. in Computer Science and Technology; Average Score: 91.27/100 Sep. 2019 - Current

Advisor: Wei Wang

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China Chengdu, China

B.Eng - Networking Engineering; GPA: 3.83/4.0 Sep. 2015 - Jul. 2019

Elite Class: Liren Leadership Class

National Chiao Tung University Taiwan, China

Exchange Student - Electrical and Computer Engineering; GPA: 4.15/4.3 Feb. 2017 - Jul. 2017

Publications and Research

mSilent: Towards General Corpus Silent Speech Recognition using COTS mmWave Radar

Shang Zeng, Haoran Wan, Shuyu Shi and Wei Wang

ACM Ubicomp/IMWUT 2023, Oct. 2023. [PDF]

VECTOR: Velocity Based Temperature-field Monitoring with Distributed Acoustic Devices

- Haoran Wan, Lei Wang, Ting Zhao, Ke Sun, Shuyu Shi, Haipeng Dai, Guihai Chen, Haodong Liu and Wei Wang ACM Ubicomp/IMWUT 2022, Sep. 2022. [PDF]
- HeadTracker: Fine-grained Head Orientation Tracking System Based on Headphones
- Jinpeng Song, Haipeng Dai, Shuyu Shi, Lei Wang, Haoran Wan, Zhizheng Yang, Fu Xiao, and Guihai Chen Springer WASA 2022, Nov. 2022. [PDF]
- RespTracker: Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking with Commercial Acoustic Devices

Haoran Wan, Shuyu Shi, Wenyu Cao, Wei Wang and Guihai Chen

IEEE INFOCOM 2021, Apr. 2021. [PDF]

- Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking using COTS Acoustic Devices
- Haoran Wan, Shuyu Shi, Wenyu Cao, Wei Wang and Guihai Chen

ACM TOSN 2022, Finished Major Revision and Resubmitted.

Extended version of INFOCOM 2021 paper

- SCALAR: Self-Calibrated Acoustic Ranging for Distributed Mobile Devices
- Lei Wang, Haoran Wan, Ting Zhao, Ke Sun, Shuyu Shi, Haipeng Dai, Guihai Chen, Haodong Liu and Wei Wang IEEE TMC 2022, Finished Major Revision and Resubmitted.
- JOG: Joint Graph and Operator level Optimizations for Deep Learning Compilation
- Zhiying Xu, Jiafan Xu, Hongding Peng, Wei Wang, Xiaoliang Wang, Haoran Wan, Haipeng Dai,

Yixu Xu, Hao Cheng, Kun Wang, and Guihai Chen

ACM EuroSys 2023, Under Review. [Arxiv]

Major Projects

• General Corpus Silent Speech Recognition with mmWave Radar

Dec. 2021 - Nov. 2022

- Did a comprehensive study on silent speech recognition with mmWave radar, the corpus is formed with 1000+ daily conversation sentences, and we collected 21K + samples as our dataset.
- o Designed a signal processing pipeline, including cluster selection algorithm to localize users' head and filter out unrelated motions.
- o Proposed a transformer-based neural network backend with user-adaptive design to recognize the speech and achieved words error rate comparable with video-based SOTA (< 10%).
- We submitted this work to IMWUT in Nov. 2022.

• Air Temperature Field Reconstruction with COTF Acoustic Devices

Apr. 2021 - May. 2022

• Estimate the air temperature with shorter response time than traditional temperature sensors by monitoring the speed changes of sound signal. Achieve average errors 0.25°C across months of evaluations.

- Combine Radon transform and Taylor Series to reconstruct the air temperature field with decimeter-level spatial resolution using multiple acoustic devices.
- Leverage LOS paths and reflections to estimate the temperature in multiple slots in a car or on the table with only one pair of devices.
- This work was accepted by Ubicomp/IMWUT 2022.

• High Accuracy Localization System between Distributed Devices

Aug. 2020 - Mar. 2021

- Model the sampling frequency offset between distributed acoustic devices precisely.
- Cancel the frequency offset and unknown delays in sound playback and recording process between devices in real time, and return the absolute distance measurement without user's intervention/calibration.
- Achieve 0.6 mm 1D localization errors up to 3 m and 1.86 mm 3D localization errors. Maintain the accuracy in long-term without performance drop (up to 8 hours).
- This work was submitted to TMC 2022.

• Multi-user Room-scale Respiration Tracking using COTS Acoustic Devices

Oct. 2019 - Aug. 2020

- Expand the acoustic based respiration sensing range to 3 m by combining multiple reflection paths.
- Separate multiple users with modulated Zadoff-Chu sequence, and can recover the breath patterns for at least 4 users in the same room simultaneously.
- o Track users by re-synchronizing the reflection signals before and after users move.
- $\circ\,$ This work was accepted by INFOCOM 2021.

• In-air Continuous Hand Gesture Recognition with Acoustic Signal

Nov. 2019 - Feb. 2020

- Develop a continuous hand gesture recognition system on mobile phone with acoustic signal, cooperating with Huawei.
- Solve the practical problem of ambiguous gestures in continuous using scenario, e.g. scrolling up is similar to the reset process of scrolling down in consecutive use.
- Design and deploy signal processing algorithm and deep learning model on mobile phone that run in real-time.

Honors and Awards

- Outstanding graduate students of Nanjing University Dec. 2021
- Huawei Graduate Scholarship Nov. 2021
- Principal Special Scholarship for Graduate Students Nov. 2019
- Second Class People's Scholarship Nov. 2016, 2018
- Undergraduate China National Scholarship, Nov. 2017

SKILLS SUMMARY

• Languages:	Python, MATLAB, Java, C/C++, SQL, Bash, Verilog
• Tools:	Scikit, Pytorch/TorchLightning, TensorFlow, Keras
• Platforms:	Linux, Raspberry, Android, FPGA, Microcontroller
D • 17 1.1.	(A) C:

• Domain Knowledge: (Array) Signal Processing, Machine Learning, Wireless Network

EXPERIENCE

Digital Logic Design and Computer Organization Teaching Assistant	Nanjing, China Sep. 2021 - Jan. 2022
• Digital Circuit and Digital System Experiment Teaching Assistant	Nanjing, China Sep. 2020 - Jan. 2021
ChinaSoft International Student Developer (Intern)	Chengdu, China Jul. 2017 - Aug. 2017
Chengdu Modern Hospital Volunteer for Elderly Care	Chengdu, China Jul. 2016